Inventory of the Günter Schmölders papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Günter Schmölders papers
1940-1985
1892-1985
85017
Hoover Institution Archives
209 manuscript boxes (83.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, conference papers, minutes, reports, financial records, and printed matter relating to economic theory, monetary policy, and economic research foundations in West Germany.
Schmölders, Günter, 1903-1991
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1985.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1903: Born, Berlin
1921-1926: Studied Sociology and Economics at the Universität zu Berlin and the Universität Tübingen
1925-1934: Assistant lecturer, Agricultural Universität Berlin
1926: Received Doctor’s degree, Universität zu Berlin (Thesis: "Failure of Prohibition Laws in Scandinavian Countries")
1930: Author, Die Prohibition in den Vereinigten Staaten
1934: Professor, Universität Breslau
1938: Author, Geld und Kredit. Probleme der Wirtschaftspolitik
1940: Professor, Universität Köln
1950-1975: Led the Finanzwissenschaftliche Forschungsinsitute at the Universität Köln
1951: Author, Allgemeine Steuerlehre
1953: Author, Organische Steuerreform
1955: Author, Konjunkturen und Krisen
1960: Founded Zentralarchiv für Empirische Sozialforschung
1965-1966: Rector, Universität Köln
1966: Author, Psychologie des Geldes
1968-1970: President, Mont Pèlerin Society
1971: Author, Der verlorene Untertan
1975: Visiting Lecturer, Institute for Humane Studies, Menlo Park, California
1991: Died, Munich
Scope and Content of Collection
Consists of two main sections, this collection documents the professional career of the German economist, Günter Schmölders. The first section is comprised of 32 subsections divided according to the subject, form, or related activity of the materials. The original arrangement and order of the materials, as created by Schmölders, has been maintained wherever possible. One section of the collection that requires addtional explanation is the Universitätsarchiv Köln file. This section was originally a separate collection of Schmölders' papers housed at the Universitätsarchiv Köln, the institution where Schmölders taught and served as rector. The majority of the materials in this section date to the years that Schmölders worked at the Universität Köln, although it also contains research files compiled during his student years. These files are maintained in their original order as arranged by the Universitätsarchiv Köln. The organization is based on the date of accession of the materials to that archive, and then loosely on the subject of the materials, which are bound and labeled. These labels have been included verbatim in this finding aid.
The Biographical file is comprised primarily of newspaper clippings of interviews and articles related to Schmölders’ professional career. Also in this section is a small amount of personal correspondence related to Schmölders’ birthday and travel.
The Correspondence file is maintained in its original order as designated by Schmölders. Correspondence is organized primarily chronologically and then alphabetically by the name of the individual or organization with whom he corresponded, or the subject discussed. There is also a small portion of correspondence separate from the chronological files organized specifically by subject. This file represents Schmölders’ correspondence beginning with his position as Professor atthe Universität Köln. Some earlier correspondence can be found in the Universitätsarchiv Köln file.
The Speeches and Writings file is comprised primarily of unpublished drafts and published copies of books, articles, and papers, spanning the entirety of Schmölders’ professional career. There is also a significant collection of lecture notes created by Schmölders, which provide outlines of speeches and university lectures. This section of the collection has been arranged alphabetically by the title of the work.
Apart from these sections, which are organized by the form of the materials, there are 16 sections that are organized by Schmölders according to their original use or related activity. In most cases, materials are grouped together by the organization, institution, or committee with which they are associated, and then chronologically. Schmölders served on many advisory boards and committees in both the private and public sector, and these activities are represented in the correspondence, reports, and meeting minutes found in these sections of the collection. More detailed descriptions of the types of materials related to specific organizations can be found in the inventory itself. Of particular note is the Mont Pèlerin Society file, which partially documents Schmölders’ membership in that organization through correspondence, reports, meeting minutes, and conference programs. More materials related to the Mont Pèlerin Society can also be found in the Universitätsarchiv Köln file.
Mont Pèlerin Society.; Economic research--Germany (West); Economics.; Economists.; Laissez-faire.; Monetary policy.
- Biographical File, 1949-1981
  - "Amerikareise,", 1975 (Box-folder 121: 5-6)
    Scope and Contents note
    Consists of itineraries, correspondence, printed matter, conference programs, speeches and writings, and writings by others related to a trip that Schmölders to the United States.
  - Birthday correspondence, 1973
    - A-G (Box-folder 121:7-122:2)
    - H-Z (Box-folder 122: 3-6)
  - Conference programs, 1977-1981 (Box-folder 122: 7)
  - Day book, 1970 (Box-folder 123: 1)
  - Interviews, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 123: 2)
  - Nebentätigkeit correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 123: 3)
    Consists of correspondence relating to Schmölders' employment collected per Germany's Nebentätigkeit requirements to document additional income received as the result of secondary jobs or outside consulting work.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1949-1977
    Consists of newspaper and magazine clippings of articles related to Schmölders' work, organized chronologically by Schmölders in binders labeled "public relations."
    - 1949-1950 (Box-folder 123: 4-6)
    - 1951-1952 (Box-folder 123:7-124:2)
    - 1953 (Box-folder 124: 3-4)
    - 1954-1955 (Box-folder 124:5-125:2)
    - 1956-1958 (Box-folder 125: 3-5)
    - 1958-1962 (Box-folder 125:6-126:2)
    - 1963-1982 (Box-folder 126:3-127:1)
    - 1970-1977 (Box-folder 127: 2-6)
  - Panel discussion transcripts, 1963-1976 (Box-folder 127: 7-8)
  - University exams, 1927-1930 (Box-folder 127: 9)
- Correspondence, 1940-1985
  - General, 1940-1985
    - October, 1940 - July, 1941 (Box-folder 21: 1-6)
    - June, 1941 - July, 1942 (Box-folder 22: 1-6)
    - July, 1942 - September, 1943 (Box-folder 23: 1-4)
    - January-December, 1970 (Box-folder 23:5-24:1)
    - January-December, 1970, A-D (Box-folder 24: 2-5)
    - January-December, 1970, E-H (Box-folder 24:6-25:3)
    - January-December, 1970, I-Q (Box-folder 25:4-26:1)
    - January-December, 1970, R-U (Box-folder 26: 2-4)
    - January-December, 1970, V-Z (Box-folder 26:5-27:1)
    - January-December, 1971 (Box-folder 27:2-30:6)
    - January-December, 1972 (Box-folder 31:1-32:4)
    - February, 1972 - December, 1973 (Box-folder 32:5-33:3)
    - January-June, 1973 (Box-folder 34: 1-3)
    - January-December, 1973 (Box-folder 34:4-35:3)
    - January-July, 1974 (Box-folder 35: 4-6)
    - January-December, 1974 (Box-folder 35:7-36:4)
    - April-October, 1974 (Box-folder 36: 5-6)
    - October, 1974 - January, 1976 (Box-folder 37: 1-5)
    - January, 1975 - November, 1976 (Box-folder 37:6-38:3)
    - January, 1975 - December, 1976 (Box-folder 38:4-39:3)
    - August-December, 1975 (Box-folder 39:4-40:1)
    - November, 1975 - May, 1977 (Box-folder 40: 2-5)
    - May-December, 1976 (Box-folder 41: 1-4)
    - January-June, 1977 (Box-folder 41:5-42:3)
    - January-July, 1977 (Box-folder 42:4-43:1)
    - January, 1977 - March, 1979 (Box-folder 43:2-5)
    - June-October, 1977 (Box-folder 43:6-44:3)
    - July-December, 1977 (Box-folder 44:4-45:3)
    - December, 1977 - March, 1978 (Box-folder 45:4-46:1)
    - July-December, 1978 (Box-folder 46: 2-6)
    - November, 1978 - January, 1979 (Box-folder 47: 1-4)
    - February-June, 1979 (Box-folder 47:5-48:2)
    - May-October, 1979 (Box-folder 48: 3-6)
    - June-December, 1979 (Box-folder 49: 1-4)
    - July, 1979 - March, 1980 (Box-folder 49:5-50:2)
    - March-June, 1980 (Box-folder 50: 3-6)
    - June-October, 1980 (Box-folder 51: 1-5)
    - September, 1980 - June, 1981 (Box-folder 51:6-52:4)
    - January-June, 1981 (Box-folder 52:5-53:2)
    - April, 1981-February, 1982 (Box-folder 53:3-6)
    - May-August, 1981 (Box-folder 54:1-4)
    - April-November, 1981 (Box-folder 54:5-55:3)
    - February-May, 1982 (Box-folder 55:4-56:1)
    - March-October, 1982 (Box-folder 56: 2-6)
    - May-November, 1982 (Box-folder 57: 1-3)
    - October-December, 1982 (Box-folder 57: 4-5)
    - January-April, 1983 (Box-folder 57:6-58:2)
    - March-July, 1983 (Box-folder 58:3-59:1)
    - June, 1983 - May, 1984 (Box-folder 59: 2-6)
    - June, 1984 - January, 1985 (Box-folder 59:7-60:3)
  - Deutsche Unesco Commission correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 60:4-61:2)
  - "Nachfolger" correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 63: 1)
  - Olympia Goldmünzen correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 61: 4-6)
  - "Ruf nach München" correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 61: 7)
    Consists of correspondence related to a job offer from the Economics Department at the University of Munich.
- Printed Matter, 1929-1982
  - "Außerordentliche öffentliche Mitgliederversammlung des Deutschen Sparkassen- und Giroverbandes am 27. Oktober 1967 in Bonn" (Box-folder 130: 5)
  - Capital Spezial, 1977 (Box-folder 130: 6)
  - Die Deutsche Volkswirtschaft, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 130: 7)
  - "Ehrenpromotion von Prof. Dr. George Katona,", 1981 (Box-folder 130: 8)
  - "Enzyklopädisches Lexikon für das Geld-, Bank-, und Börsenwesen,", undated (Box-folder 130: 9)
  - "Forschungsreport,", 1982 (Box-folder 130: 10)
  - Frihet och Ansvar, 1929 (Box-folder 130: 11)
  - General newspaper clippings, 1955-1966 (Box-folder 130: 12)
  - Gruppen Gazette, Securitas-Gilde Versicherungsgruppe newsletter, 1969 (Box-folder 130: 13)
  - "Hoffnunglose Finanzen?,", circa 1940s (Box-folder 130: 14)
  - International Background, 1982 (Box-folder 130: 15)
  - The Korean Economic Review, 1952 (Box-folder 130: 16)
  - "Leitsätze zur organischen Steuerreform,", 1949 (Box-folder 130: 17)
  - "Leopold von Wiese zum fünfundsiebzigsten Geburtstag,", 1951 (Box-folder 131: 1)
  - Neues Rheinland, 1971 (Box-folder 131: 2)
  - Perspektiven, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 131: 3)
  - Revue politique et parlementaire, 1977 (Box-folder 131: 4)
  - Steuer und Wirtschaft, 1973 (Box-folder 131: 5)
  - "Zahlen und Währungs- und Finanzreform,", circa 1940s (Box-folder 131: 6)
  - "Zehn Jahre Institut für Mittelsforschung,", 1968 (Box-folder 131: 7)
  - "Zum gedenken an Hanns Martin Schleyer,", 1977 (Box-folder 131: 8)
  - "Zur Kritik am deutschen Steuersystem,", 1951 (Box-folder 131: 9)
- Speeches and Writings, 1925-1985
  - Book reviews written by Schmölders on writings by others, 1938-1970 (Box-folder 15: 3-7)
  - Book reviews on works by Schmölders, 1955-1976 (Box-folder 4: 1-5)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 89: 4-8)
  - Encyclopaedia entries, 1964-1972 (Box-folder 16: 1-2)
  - General newspaper articles, 1929-1966 (Box-folder 16: 3-5)
  - General notes, 1956-1972 (Box-folder 16: 6-7)
    Consists of typescript notes relating to meetings and conversations with various committees, organizations, and individuals, organized alphabetically by Schmölders by name or subject.
  - Lecture notes, 1933-1982
    - "Address of Welcome to Participants of I. International Summer School on Survey Research,", undated (Box-folder 65: 1)
    - "Akademiker in der Wirtschaft,", undated (Box-folder 65: 2)
    - "Allgemeine Steuerlehre,", undated (Box-folder 65: 3)
    - "Allgemeine Volkswirschaftsleher,", circa 1960s (Box-folder 65: 4-6)
    - "Alternativen zum Sozialismus,", 1976 (Box-folder 65: 7)
    - "Attitudes to Taxation and the Effects on Work Effort,", circa 1960s (Box-folder 65: 8)
    - "Auf dem Wege zu einer konservativen Wirtschaftsphilosophie,", undated (Box-folder 65: 9)
    - "Der Beitrag des Hoteliers zum allgemeinen Unternehmen,", 1973 (Box-folder 65: 10)
    - "Die Beobachtung der allgemeinen Wirtschaftslage im Dienst der Steuerberatung,", undated (Box-folder 65: 11)
    - "Die Berücksichtig der Wirtschafts- und Arbeits- Welt in der Universitätsausbildung,", 1968 (Box-folder 65: 12)
    - "Das Bestechungsunwesen als Störungsfaktor in Ordnungssystem der Marktwirtschaft,", undated (Box-folder 65: 13)
    - "Die Besteuerung der Betriebe und Unternehmungen,", undated (Box-folder 65: 14)
    - "Betriebs und Volkswirte gehören zusammen!,", 1958 (Box-folder 65: 15)
    - "Die Beurteilung der deutschen Umsatzteuer,", 1968 (Box-folder 65: 16)
    - "Die Beziehungen zwischen Sparmotiven und Sparformen,", undated (Box-folder 65: 17)
    - "Das Bild vom Unternehmer,", circa 1970s (Box-folder 65: 18)
    - "Das Bild des Unternehmers in der öffentlichen Meinung,", circa 1970s (Box-folder 65: 19)
    - "Carl Friedrich von Siemens: Vom Leitbild eines großindustriellen Unternehmers,", 1972 (Box-folder 65: 20)
    - "Die Dauerkrise des Weltwährungssystems, psychologisch Betrachtet,", 1973 (Box-folder 65: 21)
    - "Das deutsche Steuersystem,", undated (Box-folder 65: 22)
    - "Das deutsche 'Wirtschaftswunder,'", 1953 (Box-folder 65: 23)
    - "Der deutsche Zollverein als historisches Vorbild einer wirtschaftlichen Integration in Europa,", 1953 (Box-folder 65: 24)
    - "Eigentum und Eigentumspolitik,", undated (Box-folder 65: 25)
    - "Eindrücke aus dem ostasiatischen Wirtschaftswunderland Japan,", circa 1960s (Box-folder 65: 26)
    - "Eindrücke von einer USA Reise im Sommer 1975," (Box-folder 65: 27)
    - "Der Einfluß des Zinses,", 1965 (Box-folder 65: 28)
    - "The End of 'Full Employment,'", 1976 (Box-folder 65: 29)
    - "Das Ende der 'Vollbeschäftigung' nach Jahrzehnten,", circa 1970s (Box-folder 66: 1)
    - "Die Entpolitisierung der Steuergesetzgebung,", undated (Box-folder 66: 2)
    - "Eröffnung des akademischen Festaktes anläßlich des 40-jährigen Bestehens des finanzwissenschaftlichen Forschungsinstitut,", undated (Box-folder 66: 3)
    - "Europäisch Finanzpolitik,", undated (Box-folder 66: 4)
    - "EWG und EFTA,", circa 1960s (Box-folder 66: 5)
    - "Der fehlende Einkommensbegriff,", circa 1950s (Box-folder 66: 6)
    - "Finanzielle Stabilität,", undated (Box-folder 66: 7)
    - "Finanzpolitik und Währung,", undated (Box-folder 6 6: 8)
    - "Finanzpsychologie,", undated (Box-folder 66: 9)
    - "Finanzwissenschaft I,", 1961-1962 (Box-folder 66: 10-12)
    - "Finanzwissenschaft III,", circa 1960s (Box-folder 66:13-67:1)
    - "Fiscal Psychology,", circa 1970s (Box-folder 67: 2)
    - "Die Forschungsausgabe des Institutes für Mittelstandsforschung,", 1973 (Box-folder 67: 3)
    - "Freizügigkeit der Menschen,", undated (Box-folder 67: 4)
    - "Funktion und Berufausbildung des leitenden Angestellten in der Wirtschaft von Morgen,", undated (Box-folder 67: 5)
    - "Gedanken zur organischen Steuerreform,", circa 1950s (Box-folder 67: 6)
    - "Gefahren und Schwächen der Geld- und Finanzpolitik,", 1958 (Box-folder 67: 7)
    - "Gegenwartsprobleme der Finanz- und Steuerpolitik Zeiteinteilung der Vorlesung,", 1951-1952 (Box-folder 67: 8)
    - "Geld und Kredit,", 1967-1968 (Box-folder 67: 9-12)
    - "'Geldillusion' oder 'Angst vor Geldenwertung,'", 1972 (Box-folder 67: 13)
    - "Geldwert und Vollbeschäftigung,", undated (Box-folder 67: 14)
    - General, 1965 (Box-folder 68: 1)
    - "Geschenke für die Wähler oder echte Reform?,", 1953 (Box-folder 68: 2)
    - "Geschichte der Finanzwirtschaftsliteratur,", undated (Box-folder 68: 3)
    - "Geschichte der Volkswirtschaftslehre,", circa 1960s (Box-folder 68: 4-5)
    - "Grenzen der Besteuerung,", undated (Box-folder 68: 6)
    - "Die große Verschwendung,", circa 1980s (Box-folder 68: 7)
    - "Grundlagen der organischer Steuerreform,", undated (Box-folder 68: 8)
    - "Grundsätzliches zum Steuerreform,", circa 1940s (Box-folder 68: 9)
    - "Grundsätzliches zum Steuerumbau,", undated (Box-folder 68: 10)
    - "Hat der Unternehmer noch eine Zukunft?,", 1974 (Box-folder 68: 11)
    - "Hauptpunkte des Steuernumbaus,", undated (Box-folder 68: 12)
    - "Hinkendes Wachstum,", undated (Box-folder 68: 13)
    - "Hochschulen und unternehmische Information,", undated (Box-folder 68: 14)
    - "Die Hochschule der Zukunft und der Anforderung der Wirtschaft,", 1969 (Box-folder 68: 15-16)
    - "Inflation - The German Experience,", 1974 (Box-folder 68: 17)
    - "'Inflationsmentalität'...Ein neues Schlagwort oder Mehr?,", 1973 (Box-folder 68: 18)
    - "Das Inflationsproblem als innerwirtschaftliches und als internationales Koordinationsproblem,", 1971 (Box-folder 68: 19)
    - "Ingesamt sehr positiv,", 1971 (Box-folder 68: 20)
    - "Internationale gemeinsame Grundzüge der finanzpolitischen Problematik,", circa 1950s (Box-folder 68: 21)
    - "'Internationale' und 'supramationale' Finanzpolitik,", circa 1950s (Box-folder 68: 22)
    - "Die Internationalisierung der Geld -- u. Finanzpolitik is kein Privileg unserer Tag!,", circa 1950s (Box-folder 68: 23)
    - "Der Kampf um das Wirtschafts Referendariat,", circa 1950s (Box-folder 68: 24)
    - "Kapitalbildung und Kapitalversorgung des gewerbliches Mittelstandes,", undated (Box-folder 68: 25)
    - "Kapitalbildung und Steuergesetzgebung unter besonderer Berücksichtigung des Mittelstandes,", 1952 (Box-folder 68: 26)
    - "Kapitalmarkt und Besteuerung,", 1957 (Box-folder 69: 1)
    - "Keynes und die 'Macher,'", undated (Box-folder 69: 2)
    - "Konjunkturen und Krisen,", 1961-1962 (Box-folder 69: 3)
    - "Konsum und 'Qualität' des Lebens,", undated (Box-folder 69: 4)
    - "Die Kontrolle der öffentlichen Ausgaben und Kritik des Haushalts durch die Steuerzahler,", undated (Box-folder 69: 5)
    - "Kreditpolitik un Konjunkturpolitik,", circa 1950s (Box-folder 69: 6)
    - "Die Krise zwischen Staatsbürger und Obrigkeit,", undated (Box-folder 69: 7)
    - "Kritik und Reform der körperschaftsteuer,", 1953 (Box-folder 69: 8)
    - "Laudatio auf Dr. Willy Haubrichs,", 1976 (Box-folder 69: 9)
    - "Leistungsanforderungen und Berufsvorbildung im öffentlichen Dienst,", circa 1970s (Box-folder 69: 10)
    - "Leistungsgedenke und Steuerpolitik,", undated (Box-folder 69: 11)
    - "Macht und Ohnmacht des Verbrauchers,", 1967 (Box-folder 69: 12)
    - "Der 'Maßstab' des 'Maßhaltens,'", 1962 (Box-folder 69: 13)
    - "Mehr Demokratie - Mehr Inflation?,", undated (Box-folder 69: 14)
    - "Moloch Staat,", circa 1970s (Box-folder 69: 15)
    - "Die multinationalen Gesellschaften,", circa 1970s (Box-folder 69: 16)
    - "Namens und sein Austrage unseres heirathenden Präsidenten,", undated (Box-folder 69: 17)
    - "'O.V.F.' als interdisziplinäre Erkenntnisquelle?,", circa 1950s (Box-folder 69: 18)
    - "Das Ordnungsprinzip 'sozial Markwirtschaft' und seine Gefährdungen,", 1978 (Box-folder 69: 19)
    - "Organische Steuerreform,", 1952-1953 (Box-folder 69: 20)
    - "Organische Steuerreform und Großhandel,", undated (Box-folder 69: 21)
    - "Öffentlichen Ausgaben -- ein Anliegen der Steuerzahlen?,", undated (Box-folder 69: 22)
    - "Öffentlichkeitsarbeit der deutschen Hochschulen,", 1967 (Box-folder 69: 23)
    - "Ökonomische Verhaltensforschung,", 1955-1956 (Box-folder 69: 24)
    - "Ökonomische Verhaltensforschung - dargestellt an der aktuellen Auf- und Abwertungsdiskussion,", circa 1950s (Box-folder 69: 25)
    - "Die Politiker und die Steuern,", 1956 (Box-folder 69: 26)
    - "Die Politiker und die Währung,", circa 1960s (Box-folder 69: 27-28)
    - "Politische und institutionelle Aspekte der Budgetgliederung,", undated (Box-folder 69: 29)
    - "Porträt des deutschen Unternehmers,", 1971 (Box-folder 69: 30)
    - "Preisbildung und Preisprüfung,", 1939-1945, undated (Box-folder 69: 31)
    - "Problematik der Kapitalbildung und Kapitalversorgung des gewerblichen Mittelstandes,", circa 1950s (Box-folder 69: 32)
    - "Probleme der Geldwirtschaft in Europa,", 1948 (Box-folder 70: 1)
    - "Probleme der Geldwirtschaft in Europa...uferlos!,", 1947 (Box-folder 70: 2)
    - "Probleme einer mittelstandorientieren Steuerpolitik,", 1964 (Box-folder 70: 3)
    - "Prognosen, Prognosen...,", 1975 (Box-folder 70: 4)
    - "La psychologie financière,", circa 1960s (Box-folder 70: 5)
    - "Psychologie des Geldes,", undated (Box-folder 70: 6)
    - "Psychologische Aspekte der europäischen Integration,", undated (Box-folder 70: 7)
    - "Psychologische Aspekte der Geldwertstabilität,", 1967 (Box-folder 70: 8)
    - "Psychologische Aspekte der neuen Finanz- und Wirtschaftspolitik,", 1967 (Box-folder 70: 9)
    - "Psychologie fiscale,", 1970 (Box-folder 70: 10)
    - "Psychologische Probleme der Steuerharmonisierung im gemeinsamen Markt,", 1963 (Box-folder 70: 11)
    - "Restriktive Stabilitätspolitik als Kommunalpolitik oder als Mittel der Inflationsbekämpfung,", 1974 (Box-folder 70: 12)
    - "Die Rolle der Psychologie in der Volkswirtschaft,", undated (Box-folder 70: 13)
    - "Rückblick auf 1963," (Box-folder 70: 14)
    - "Rüstungsfinanzierung und Währung,", 1955 (Box-folder 70: 15)
    - "Der sanfte Tod des Rentners (Schicksale einer Prognose),", undated (Box-folder 70: 16)
    - "Schattenwirschaftschau,", undated (Box-folder 70: 17)
    - "Der schlitzohrige Staatsbürger,", 1971 (Box-folder 70: 18)
    - "Die 'Schlüsselzuweisungen,'", undated (Box-folder 70: 19)
    - "Selbstfinanzierung und Besteuerung,", 1962 (Box-folder 70: 20)
    - "Der sogenannte Lastenausgleich als finanzwirtschaftliches Problem,", undated (Box-folder 70: 21)
    - "Sozialökonomische Verhaltensforschung,", 1962-1963 (Box-folder 70:22-71:2)
    - "Sozialökonomische Verhaltensforschung (besser: 'anthropologische Sozialökonomik'),", circa 1970s (Box-folder 71: 3)
    - "So zeigt sich die deutsche Finanzwirtschafte heute,", 1981 (Box-folder 71: 4)
    - "Der Sparer im Mittelpunkt der Wirtschaft,", undated (Box-folder 71: 5)
    - "Das Sparhalten der Deutschen,", 1965 (Box-folder 71: 6)
    - "Staatsausgaben und Währung,", circa 1950s (Box-folder 71: 7)
    - "Staatsbürgerliche Gesinnung und Steuermoral,", undated (Box-folder 71: 8)
    - "Staatsfinanzen und Staatskredit,", undated (Box-folder 71: 9)
    - "Stabile Währung -- gezügelte Finanzen,", circa 1950s (Box-folder 71: 10)
    - "Stand und Aussichten der organischen Steuerreform,", circa 1950s (Box-folder 71: 11)
    - "Die Stellung des Unternehmers in der Wirtschafts und Gesellschaftspolitik,", 1972 (Box-folder 71: 12)
    - "Steuer-Harmonisierung,", undated (Box-folder 71: 13)
    - "Die Steuer als Instrument der Währungspolitik,", undated (Box-folder 71: 14)
    - "Steuerliche Weltbewerbsverzerrungen,", undated (Box-folder 71: 15)
    - "Steuermentalität,", 1967 (Box-folder 71: 16)